Guide to the James M. Robb Collection SC0652
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
James M. Robb collection
1938-2008
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Marks, Allison Robb
Robb, James M.
Garred, Jannis Robb
SC0652
1.75 Linear Feet
This collection includes typescripts of James M. Robb's manuscript "Carry On" written while he was a patient at the Bilibid prison-hospital in the Philippines during World War II; correspondence from his parents' efforts to locate the manuscript, 1946-48; reports and documents pertaining to Japanese treatment of Philippine prisoners of war, especially the "Hell Ships" that transported POWs to Japan; resources collected by his sister Marion Robb about the history of POWs in the Philippines with related correspondence, 1980-98; and additional family materials from his daughters Jannis Robb Garred and Allison Robb Marks, including a letter (photocopied) from James M. Robb to his wife, 1938.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Marion Robb, 2002; additional materials from Jannis R. Garred and Allison R. Marks, 2008.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
James M. Robb earned his A.B. in political science at Stanford in 1931 and his law degree in 1934. He worked for three years with the Oakland Title Company before returning to Manila in 1937, where he joined the law firm of DeWitt, Perkins and Ponce Enrile. When World War II broke out, he enlisted in the U.S. Army and was a first lieutenant in the Quartermaster Department during the siege of Bataan. He survived the Bataan death march and several POW camps in the Philippines, but died at sea in January 1945 while being transported with other POWs to Japan. Robb worked on a book detailing wartime conditions in the Philippines and the POW camps while he was a patient at the Bilibid prison-hospital; the manuscript was buried for safekeeping and retrieved when American troops liberated the Philippines.
Description of the Collection
This collection includes typescripts of James M. Robb's manuscript "Carry On" written while he was a patient at the Bilibid prison-hospital in the Philippines during World War II; correspondence from his parents' efforts to locate the manuscript, 1946-48; reports and documents pertaining to Japanese treatment of Philippine prisoners of war, especially the "Hell Ships" that transported POWs to Japan; resources collected by his sister Marion Robb about the history of POWs in the Philippines with related correspondence, 1980-98; and additional family materials from his daughters Jannis Robb Garred and Allison Robb Marks, including a letter (photocopied) from James M. Robb to his wife, 1938.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Prisoners and prisons, Japanese.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Concentration camps -- Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Philippines.; Marks, Allison Robb; Robb, James M.; Robb, James M.; Garred, Jannis Robb; Robb, Marion.; Bilibid Prison (Manila, Philippines).
- Papers
  - Buried Manuscript "Carry On" – typescript, copy 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Buried Manuscript "Carry On" – typescript, photocopy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AP dispatches on Japanese atrocities in Manila, April 2, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Capas Prisoners of War Memorial – correspondence, proposal, article, 1980-83 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous, 1945-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ex-POW Bulletin, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ex-POW Bulletin, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Ex-POW Bulletin, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hell Ships – reports, clippings, correspondence, 1945-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Oryoku Maru Story, prepared by Charles M. Brown, Lt. Col. AUS ret., 1982 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reports on American Prisoners of War Interned by the Japanese in the Philippines, prepared by the office of the Provost Marshal General, 19 November 1945 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Resource materials collected by Marion Robb (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Robb, James M. – Purple Heart documents (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Robb, Marion – correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Robb, Marion – statement re claims of heirs to the manuscript, 1995; and statements from Robb’s daughters, Jannis Robb Garred and Allison Robb Marks, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Robb, Mr. and Mrs. Walter J. – correspondence re obtaining manuscript, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Shinyo Maru – list of casualties and survivors (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Steele, Ben – copy of undated letter with mention of Robb and copy of a Steele's sketch of Robb while a POW in the Philippines (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Samuel B. Moody and Maury Allen, Reprieve from Hell (1961) (Box 3)
  - Samuel B. Moody, Reprieve from Hell Part II, 1 videotape(s) (vhs) (Box 3)
  - Last message from Corregidor, 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Correspondence between Prof. David Kennedy and Jannis Robb Garred and Allison Robb Marks, 2002, with photocopied resources on James M. Robb’s life, 1946-47 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Copy of “Carry On” by James M. Robb with introduction by Jannis Robb Garred and Allison Robb Marks (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - von Neff, Erich correspondence re: James M. Robb, 1983-1992 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Address, 1943-03-02 (Box 1, Folder 3)